let's move now to demand paging I'm going to
repeat some concept because I think uh it's good
for virtual memory to repeat some stuff so that
you can hopefully digest it better so we said that
we could bring the entire process into memory
when we want to start the process but in practice
we can be more efficient if we just bring parts of
it and then react when the process needs something
that is not in memory and this is of course
beneficial because you generate less input output
you need less memory which means you can run
more processes or allow more users to run
more processes of course you need to double
check that if the process tries to access a page
and actually that page is not loaded in any
frame then you take the actions needed to firstly
put the page in a frame and then tell the
process okay now you can access the page
you can go with different strategies here you
can go for something that is extremely easy
and then basically start a process without
actually loading any page as soon as the process
asks for the very first address or the
very first instruction it will immediately
generate an interrupt because you need to wake
up the operating system and put at least the
first page into the frame so of course
it's not practical you would start the process by
putting actually some page because you already
know that at least the initial ones will be
needed but from a theoretical perspective
you can even go with this lazy swapper
it can be used actually even in practice so
let's go through some basic concepts again
we have a pager that is the one that brings
the pages into the frames when it's needed
it's more complicated than just a paging
system that takes all the pages and loads
all of them in a frame before starting a process
in practice you need to have extra functionality
in the memory management unit we will see as
always you need to pay the costs either in
time or in space we will see that we pay in
both space and time space when it comes to the
page table and time when it comes to the time it
actually takes to access a page if it is not there
of course if the page is already there fine
then nothing needs to be done when the
page is not there then we need to detect that
and load the page before the process can actually
access it and of course we want to do this
dealing with this kind of problems at the
operating system level so when you write
a program and you run a program you don't
write such a program so that is compatible
with a system that uses virtual memory
actually your laptop is using virtual memory but
when you write your program you just ignore so
this is all things that are done by the
operating system in collaboration with
the hardware so the first thing here we need is to
know is the page that i want to access in memory
or not? to do this we enrich the table putting a
bit in each entry which is the valid invalid bit
if it's valid it means then yes then the page is
in the frame if it's invalid it means the page is
not loaded yet so first I need to load the page
and then I in this case is the operating system
and then you can access the page so this
information is actually used this valid invalid
bit by the memory management unit when it does
the translation to check if it's valid or not
if the page is in memory or not so this is
how it could look like right we have eight
pages here but only three are in the physical
memory in three frames and those have the
bit set to valid while all the other bits
all the other entries are set to invalid
so page fault is what we call this event
of trying to access a page and finding out
that that page has not been loaded into a frame
when we say there has been a page fault this is
what we are talking about when there is a
page fault the hardware generates an interrupt
the operating system wakes up checks what's the
cause of the page fault and if it's about
something that is not being loaded in memory
then it loads the missing page into a frame
and tells the process that okay it can start
again the operating system needs to find a
a frame that is free we will see that sometimes all
the frames might be used and the operating system
also needs to take decisions when that happens
then it swaps the page only one page into the
frame and this of course is a disk
operation because you need to read
it updates the page table saying that now
the reference is actually valid and then
it can restart the process that is trying to
run and this is basically what I just said
but you have the steps number here and the
different actions have a look at the figure
as I said you can go with a very lazy approach
you can call this it's called pure demand paging
and start a process with no pages in memory
okay as soon as it starts requesting pages
you will get page faults and it will keep
loading pages as needed by the process
I mentioned this before many times it's
collaboration between operating system
and hardware and here you can already see the
collaboration now we already discussed some
of it you need to enrich the page table so
actually what you store close to the CPU in some
register to do the translation with this valid
invalid bit so the hardware is actually prepared
to use valid invalid bits you need the ability to
restart an instruction you try to run something
the operating system needs to wake up and replace
or load the page into a frame and then you need
hardware support so that you can tell the process
try again to run the next instruction because the
previous run was not successful because there
was no page in a frame and you can also rely
on the hardware using the so-called swap space
basically you can take a portion of the disk
and use it as if it was an extension of the memory
to keep only pages that you are swapping in
and out when you are doing this when you react to
the page faults
it is costly this I said you need to
generate a trap to the operating system you need
to save registers and process state there will be
a context switch you need to wake up the operating
system the operating system needs to understand
why it is being wakened up so what is this interrupt
about find out that it's a page fault double
check if it's just a matter of loading a page
into a frame or if it was a page fault because the
process maybe was trying to access actually memory
that does not belong to it it needs to issue
a read request from the disk and so on so
just read this sequence I already mentioned it
what I'm trying to say here is that there are a
lot of operations okay actually you can get
an estimate of how bad it can get right so
you have three major activities you need to
service the interrupt you need to read the page
and then you need to restart the process if you
define p to be the page fault rate zero means
there is no page fault basically it means you load
everything into memory so it's paging without
virtual memory one it's the laziest approach means
every time you need a page you need to first load
it because it's not in memory then you can compute
the effective access time as one minus p times
memory access plus p the percentage the portion of
requests that are actually generating a page fault
times the page fault overhead swap of the page out
so swapping of the page out if you actually need
to free a frame swap in of the page
when you load the page that is missing